<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Assignment overview | Spatial Data in R</title>
    <link>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Assignment overview</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/media/icon_hucbe598379047767cc1c1c9b182811605_98018_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Assignment overview</title>
      <link>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to class resources and data structures in R</title>
      <link>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/04-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/04-exercise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is here for ease of reference; you should complete your assignment using your individual GitHub Classroom repositories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-assignment&#34;&gt;Your assignment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal for this assignment is to ensure that you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;have access to our Rstudio server and shared data folder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;can access the assignments in Github Classroom&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;are able to determine what data structure you&amp;rsquo;re working with and what data types are contained with the object&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;can succesfully knit an Rmarkdown document to html&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1-load-your-packages&#34;&gt;Step 1: Load your packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I do this in one code chunk at the beginning of the Rmarkdown document so that users know exactly what packages they&amp;rsquo;ll need and can make decisions about if/how they want to install them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(tidyverse)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ── Attaching packages ─────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse 1.3.1 ──
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ✓ ggplot2 3.3.5     ✓ purrr   0.3.4
## ✓ tibble  3.1.3     ✓ dplyr   1.0.7
## ✓ tidyr   1.1.3     ✓ stringr 1.4.0
## ✓ readr   2.0.0     ✓ forcats 0.5.1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## ── Conflicts ────────────────────────────────────────── tidyverse_conflicts() ──
## x dplyr::filter() masks stats::filter()
## x dplyr::lag()    masks stats::lag()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2-load-the-data&#34;&gt;Step 2: Load the data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next few weeks, we&amp;rsquo;ll be using data from the High Country News &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.landgrabu.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Land Grab University&lt;/a&gt; project. These data depict the role of expropriated Indigenous land in funding the fifty-two land-grant universities in the United States. They contain information on nearly 11 million acres of Indigenous land tanke from ~250 tribes, bands and communities through a multitude of treaties and violent land seizures. Check it out as it will help you understand what these data are depicting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;csv.list &amp;lt;- list.files(&#39;/opt/data/session02/CSVs/&#39;, pattern = &amp;quot;*.csv&amp;quot;, full.names = TRUE)
data &amp;lt;- lapply(csv.list, function (x) read.csv(x))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question 1: what is &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; doing in the statement above?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question 2: what type of data is contained in the 3 column of the 2nd element of the &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; object? (show the code you used to figure it out by inserting a code chunk)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question 3: what happens if you run the above code with the the &lt;code&gt;read_csv&lt;/code&gt; function from the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; package?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question 4: Use the first element of the &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; object to determine the total amount paid for the land depicted in that object (HINT: you&amp;rsquo;ll need to coerce the data into a different format)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember - edit this document and knit to .html within your GitHub Classroom repo and &lt;em&gt;commit&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;push&lt;/em&gt; those changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final Project: Analyze your data</title>
      <link>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/03-finalproj/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/03-finalproj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;reminder-of-the-class-project&#34;&gt;Reminder of the class project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mini-projects and final project are intended to give you the chance to practice the workflows and techniques that we cover in class in the context of a complete analysis. Because each of you are in different stages of collecting your own data and because confronting datasets that aren&amp;rsquo;t yours can help clarify important concepts and design elements, I&amp;rsquo;m asking you to develop an analysis of data that &lt;strong&gt;isn&amp;rsquo;t yours&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have you gain some experience finding spatial data, thinking about an interesting question where the geographic location is (at least partially) important in determining how we might think about the process that gives rise to the data, and developing an analysis and suite of visualizations that help you (and others) better understand that process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-project&#34;&gt;Final Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now you&amp;rsquo;ve built a spatial database with a variety of predictors and visualized that data to start to develop some potential hypotheses about how the data relate to each other. The last step is to evaluate your &amp;lsquo;hypotheses&amp;rsquo; (using that term loosely because this is, hopefully, an area outside of your expertise) with a statistical model like the few we&amp;rsquo;ve looked at in the last portion of the class. For your final project, I want you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fit two different kinds of models (e.g. logistic regression and random forest; or, better yet, use the &lt;code&gt;dismo&lt;/code&gt; vignette and use some of the additional classifiers there; or, better still, read some of the Introduction to Statistical Learning book and use classification approaches described there).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each model-type, fit a global model (i.e., a model that contains all of the predictors you&amp;rsquo;ve developed) and a reduced model (i.e., a model with only the handful of predictors you imagine to be important based on your visualizations). You should have a total of 4 different model objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generate the confusion matrix and AUC for each model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use k-fold cross-validation (see the vignettes for dismo and Intro to Statistical Learning) to evaluate the preictive accuracy of each model&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plot the spatial predictions from the best model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submit a knit-able Rmarkdown document that resembles a publishable manuscript. You should have an Introduction that describes the question you are asking, why that interests you, and the hypothses you intend to evaluate (1-2 paragraphs, max). You don&amp;rsquo;t have to have an exhaustive literature search (or any citations at all, really) just set up the analysis you are hoping to do. You should have a methods section that describes your approach to manipulating the data (with code chunks) and justifies assumptions or modifications you made along the way. You should be able to put the plots of your results, AUC and confusion matrices, and Cross-validation results in a Results section. Finally, you should close with an interpretation of your results that includes some reflection on which model was the best for your question and why (2-3 paragraphs, max).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mini-Project 1: Building a spatial database</title>
      <link>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/01-miniproj1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/01-miniproj1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-the-class-project&#34;&gt;Overview of the class project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mini-projects and final project are intended to give you the chance to practice the workflows and techniques that we cover in class in the context of a complete analysis. Because each of you are in different stages of collecting your own data and because confronting datasets that aren&amp;rsquo;t yours can help clarify important concepts and design elements, I&amp;rsquo;m asking you to develop an analysis of data that &lt;strong&gt;isn&amp;rsquo;t yours&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have you gain some experience finding spatial data, thinking about an interesting question where the geographic location is (at least partially) important in determining how we might think about the process that gives rise to the data, and developing an analysis and suite of visualizations that help you (and others) better understand that process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mini-project-1&#34;&gt;Mini-project 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals for this phase of your final project are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articulate an interesting research question based on a dataset you&amp;rsquo;d like to learn more about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Develop a spatial database that contains potentially relevant explanatory variables that you&amp;rsquo;d like to explore in the context of that research question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrate an understanding of the various workflow elements involved in designing and constructing a spatial database for subsequent visualization and analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;finding-data&#34;&gt;Finding Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step in developing your projects will be figuring out what question you&amp;rsquo;d like to ask and what data you&amp;rsquo;ll need to get there. There&amp;rsquo;s a never-ending list of available data online, but you might start with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/resource/data/&#34;&gt;Data Resources Page&lt;/a&gt;. You&amp;rsquo;re welcome to explore data that might end up being a part of your research (e.g., Census Data, landcover data), but I would encourage you to use the data to answer a question that isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily the focus of your research. This will give you the opportunity to learn about the data while also zooming out from your research questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-assignment&#34;&gt;The assignment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, you&amp;rsquo;ll need a dependent variable and a number of explanatory variables organized in a format that will allow you to visualize and analyze them effectively and efficiently. To that end, I&amp;rsquo;d like you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a dependent variable that has a point geometry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose sensible &amp;lsquo;regions&amp;rsquo; (e.g., counties, ecoregions, watersheds, nations) that might serve to organize higher-order variables that describe the process that gives rise to your dependent variable. These should have a polygon or multipolygon geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a suite (at least 3 variables) of tabular data that can be joined to either your points or regions to help further describe the context of the process of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose a suite (at least 3 variables) of spatial data (polygon or raster, at least 1 raster) of spatial data that can be joined to your database using &lt;code&gt;terra::extract&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;terra::zonal&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;st_join&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Construct your database using spatial and tabular joins and raster extractions, use &lt;code&gt;summarise&lt;/code&gt; to generate at least one aggregated estimate at the regional level and &lt;code&gt;mutate&lt;/code&gt; to create a new predictor that is derived from the data you&amp;rsquo;ve collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turn in a .Rmarkdown document that describes your research question, provides a brief overview of each dataset you are using (1-2 sentences describing what the data is, where it came from, and why you think it&amp;rsquo;s relevant), and provides all of the necessary code (with annotation) to reproduce the production of your database. (&lt;strong&gt;Remember this last bit is important as I&amp;rsquo;ll need to be able to reproduce your analysis from end-to-end&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mini-Project 2: Visualizing your data</title>
      <link>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/02-miniproj2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://isdrfall21.classes.spaseslab.com/assignment/02-miniproj2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;reminder-of-the-class-project&#34;&gt;Reminder of the class project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mini-projects and final project are intended to give you the chance to practice the workflows and techniques that we cover in class in the context of a complete analysis. Because each of you are in different stages of collecting your own data and because confronting datasets that aren&amp;rsquo;t yours can help clarify important concepts and design elements, I&amp;rsquo;m asking you to develop an analysis of data that &lt;strong&gt;isn&amp;rsquo;t yours&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have you gain some experience finding spatial data, thinking about an interesting question where the geographic location is (at least partially) important in determining how we might think about the process that gives rise to the data, and developing an analysis and suite of visualizations that help you (and others) better understand that process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mini-project-2&#34;&gt;Mini-project 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you&amp;rsquo;ve built a spatial database, it&amp;rsquo;s time to start making some sense of it. One way to do that is by visualizing the data, either using maps or other types of plots. That&amp;rsquo;s the goal of this assignment. Given your research question and &amp;lsquo;hypotheses&amp;rsquo; (I&amp;rsquo;m using this term loosely because you are [hopefully] using data that you&amp;rsquo;re not terribly familiar with), this project asks you to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Develop two static maps that display the relationship between your dependent variables and one or more of your predictor variables&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Develop one interactive map that allows you to explore potential correlations/relations between your &lt;strong&gt;predictor&lt;/strong&gt; variables&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Develop two additional non-spatial visualizations that attempt to characterize the same relations without using a map&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Submit a knittable Rmarkdown document that describes your research question and what you hope to learn from the visualizations you develop. Your document should also include reflections on the effectiveness of each visualization. How does mapping help or confuse relationships? How do interactive maps facilitate different kinds of explorations compared with static maps? How does what you&amp;rsquo;ve learned about these different visualizations inform how you might approach planning an analysis and presenting the results? As always, your document should also include well-annotated code that allows me to reproduce the figures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
